Aloha, sorry that I can't be there with you guys today, but I got called into jury duty.
Anyway, what I want to do is get you started on Lab 2 in this video. Let's get started on
Lab 2. Yeah, what we're going to do is build some gates using NAND gates. Okay, just to show that NAND is
universal. And then we'll also turn a finished circuit into a subcircuit and put it inside another circuit. We'll look quickly at splitters and
tunnels and then lay out De Morgan's second law which would light an LED if it ever failed. I'm not going to do that one
For you because you're going to do a bunch of them yourself. Okay, so basically I'm going to do NAND_NOT guided in the lab —
we'll go through it step by step and build it and then we'll do NAND_AND. You're going to have to derive the NAND_OR.
Notice. These are all part of Assignment 2 so you're actually working on Assignment 2 and Lab 2 overlap a little bit. Okay, so
You're gonna have to derive the NAND_OR. Notice XOR from NAND Not in the assignment — practice.
That's for you to do.
The DeMorgan2 check. These say "not in the assignment," but they should still be in your lab.
These two the Boolean expression and the DeMorgan2 check those are part of your Assignment 2 so we're not gonna touch them here.
Okay, so this one proves De Morgan's first law this one over here for the lab proves De Morgan's second law so you
need your lab should include NAND_NOT, NAND_AND, NAND_OR and XOR from NAND.
Okay semester file rename it you can rename it outside Logisim, or open it and rename it, which is what I did I opened it in here and
then I renamed it now I'm going to be playing with this one.
Okay, so this is you know here's our information you know here's our information you know here's our information up
in the corner it's not open yet so let me open the file File, Open Recent you can see I renamed it —
there are two of them I think this is the one we did last week.
Okay, and you can see inside here I have main and ByteReader and you can open ByteReader and you can see what ByteReader looks
like. All right, so now we'll get into the lab so let me blow this up to take the whole screen.
And go into the lab. Okay, so I renamed it so we're going to add a circuit. Okay, it's an empty circuit and we're
going to name that NAND_NOT okay so it's a NOT gate from a nand gate.
All right, that's what we're going to do so let's go in here and.
Let's uh wow that's off the screen let's shrink that down I'm sorry it needs to be so that we can see it.
Okay so in here we're gonna go Project, Add Circuit my circuit name it's going
to be NAND_NOT say. Okay, and then over here we look and you see it's here it has the magnifying glass over it that
means that's the one we've selected. All right, so let me get rid of that.
Okay so from our gates we'll open up our gates and we're going to grab a nand gate and we're going to put it
in and we're going to make it two inputs. All right, so from the input side we'll have
two inputs we're making a NOT gate so I'll make this two inputs this.
Okay, we're making a NOT gate so it has one input and what we're going to do is we're going to take that input
and we're going to split it and put it into both inputs of the NAND all right so here's our input we'll grab one
of those and we'll just butt it up against this one you see it's connected they're all dark green let's label this one A.
Okay and we have one output make a little wire we'll grab the round one we'll put it on the end it's connected and
we'll call it Y and it's going we're going to change three-state from Yes to No.
Okay, so here's our nand gate.
Okay that operates like a NOT gate and so how do we know that.
Okay, so we know we have A and Y and y right so for a NOT
gate, when A is zero y is one.
I don't know if I did very good there that's not bad.
You use Ctrl+D to duplicate. Okay, text tool to edit it and when A is one.
Y of zero so that's our kind of our truth table right NOT gate. Okay, so with the poke tool: A is zero, Y
is one — that's the first row when A is 1, Y is 0 — that's the second row.
So this is our NAND gate, our NOT gate, from a NAND.
Okay, that's it right there, that's NOT from NAND. So that's the first one, when you put one output, place the pins
— an input pin on the left and output pin on the right.
Okay, label A, Y. Okay, all right, place a NAND gate from the gates.
Okay, see its number of inputs at 2, wire it A to both NAND inputs.
Okay, so check when A is 0, it should be 1. Okay, so that's everything.
Now, now we want an AND from NAND. Okay, so that's everything.
Now, now we want an AND from NAND. Okay, so now we want an AND from NAND.
Not a NOT, we want AND from NAND. All right. So we have 2 inputs, A and B and output Y.
Let's create that circuit first. So we're gonna go up here. Project.
Add circuit. NAND. And there's our blank one, we have
two inputs, A, A, and I can use Ctrl+D to duplicate it,
Z this way, and this one is B, and we have one
output, output, call it Y, and set three-state to No, and then we have some NAND gates, and we have to put
in NAND gates. Okay, so now what we've got to do is figure out how to make
this work, so that it works. So let's look at the instructions, okay.
Place a NAND gate, wire A to the upper input and B to the lower input.
Now it's in. A times B, not, right?
Okay, so what I want to do here, and this one down here, we're going to move this one there, this one there, we
have A goes in, B goes in, and we have an output, and we have a NAND gate.
So this is our Y. So this is a NAND gate. The output is now (A AND B)', right, because that's what NAND is.
Invert, we should already know, which means we want to NAND it
again, and not it, so that we get A times B — because A times B, NOTed twice.
So we have A, NAND gate. Is the same as a times B okay so we know what we have a NOT gate created
it from NAND gates already so let's go in here and let me show you we could.
Okay, we could put an and gate in here. Okay, make it a two input two input and then connect
these two right and then connect this to the output. Okay, so when either is zero or one output
is zero for an AND gate and when they're both 1, the output is 1.
Okay, so they're both 0, it's 0, when A is 1, it's still 0, when A is 0, 1, it's still 0, when it's
1, 1, it's 1. So we have an AND gate. All right, that's how you build an AND gate from NAND gates.
Now, what we could have done, and this is elsewhere in the thing,.
Is kind of taken the NOT gate from the NANDs and dropped it in.
We have an input, there's a NOT gate, we have an output.
Okay, and notice when we do this, I'm going to either use my input or I'm going to use my input, and then I'm
going to OK, either input, or I'm going to OK, either input, or I'm going to OK, either input, or I'm going to OK,
or I'm going to OK, and notice when we do this, is zero the output is still zero when they're both one the output
is one. Okay, you want to see what this inside here you can double click on the middle and we can see it's an
and gate because that's what we had from before. Okay, so we're reusing this in our hand right so since the NAND_NOT it's just
a NAND gate with one input pipe to both of it and one output. Okay, when we put that in this NAND_AND
gate this is the same.
Okay so this box is this shape with one input split to a NAND gate and
one output out to Y right because when I double click when I go to this middle of this.
I can't if I can't get the double click again right click and go view right that's all it is that's what that box
is has one input and one output, with the input feeding both sides of a NAND gate and the output is the output from NAND right
that's how you can drag and drop and use things you've already created in other things.
Okay, and then typically what I would have done instead is I would have and this isn't anywhere in this assignment but I would
have to see this NAND_NOT I would go open that and I would right click and go Edit Circuit Appearance.
Okay, here's my circuit.
Okay I have an input and an output on a NOT gate you see a NOT gate use what
are not gay looks like I could draw a triangle with a circle on it, with an input and an output. Okay, so so
if I go to NAND_NOT and if I want to Edit Circuit Appearance and yep to Edit Circuit Appearance here's what it looks like
well what I could do is I could redraw this.
Change that.
I'm going to draw it like this.
So I have a triangle I can make the input I can take this input move it there the output this dot is the
rotation point let me put it up on top so it rotates around that point and get rid of all those don't need it
I have input output oh wait let me move this output over one move it over here and then let me draw a circle.
Right there so now I have a circle with the output and an input.
Now what's going to happen is when I look at NAND_AND see this it changes the shape of it let me move it over
here let me delete all that.
Input, output, Y, reset
my simulation. Poke tool, okay, now this one, I redrew it
to look like this one, but it's actually this one here. And you know it because, right here, over
here, you know it because if I click on this and I go.
So it's not. It's the NAND_NOT circuit, and I can view it, and that's what you get.
Okay so I like to redraw my circuits when I create them so that when I look at them and I use them in
other circuits they look proper. Okay anyway, that's a lot of stuff to just do this simple, create this, okay, and then here's a
little thing. You can check all these things here, all right,
so, so Logisim Classic, I just did all this, but
not in this exact example. And you can do this example, but it's exactly the same if you wanted to look at this one
and you wanted to use it, so if I'm in main, let's get rid of this one, and I wanted to use this one
in a circuit, I could drop it in, now it automatically looks like a box.
I have A and B, you can see when I roll over them they say A and B.
You know that one doesn't say Y. So, A, B, and Y.
Well, I don't like this shape. I don't like it at all.
So I can go into NAND and, and I can edit the Circuit Appearance.
So here I got, this is the rotation point, here's my output, okay, now when I click on these, the little circuit appears in
the middle, okay, and I can see that I'm in the middle of the circuit.
Yeah. So, as you can see, the little circuit appears in the lower right hand corner.
Let me see if I can, so it's up, so, when I click on one of these, down in the right hand corner, you
can see it's blown up and that shows it's B. The bottom one, okay.
That's how you'd know which of these which are A, which are B, okay.
We draw that, so I don't like this drawing, I want it to look like an actual NAND gate.
Okay, so a NAND gate, let's see, look
like this one, not really, that doesn't look
like. Let's see, what we
want is, we want something stylized.
This, okay, and then this one we want, uh, to do,
to do, to do, no, we want more than fill.
That's what it works. Right, this is my NAND gate with a circle on the end.
And then I have an output pin, and I have my two input pins.
I don't want to get rid of that green one, dot, green one is my rotation, I'm going to put it right there, I
don't need this, and then if I want text, I can go, I need one for A, for my A input, I need one
for B, for my B input, I need one for Y, for my Y output, okay, and then I can say.
So I wrote those, you can only write single line, but let's put A right here, and B, you can put them on the
inside, you don't have to, but I like putting them on the inside.
This is a NAND gate, and this is Y. Okay, so that's just how it looks.
Now if I go back to main, where I had input, I'm going to go back to main.
Now I have inputted one, right, it changed what it looked like to what I just did.
Not a great diagram, it doesn't really look like this. Okay, but I'm just building it.
There's the Circuit Appearance, right, you have these shapes. So I could have done.
Oh, I could have done that. Have built an arc. What I normally do
is with a built an arc, like.
This, put that on a rectangle, so maybe that's a little bit
better. Or what you could do is once you do this, the other way you can do it is you get rid of the
arc and you can do it by hand with straight lines. There's a line.
There's a line. There's a line. Right? Do something
like that to get that shape. It looks closer. It's not good, but it's closer.
All right, and then you can put your
A, your B, rotation, my circle, my output,
my Y, and my NAND. My A input and my B input.
And delete that stuff. So now when I go here, so anywhere I've used that circuit, it redrew it.
Okay? To be just like whatever I drew it. All right, so that's how you use Circuit Appearance.
Now you build circuits, and then how you reuse them in other places.
Okay, OR from NAND, that's up to you to figure out how to do.
XOR from NAND, that's up to you to figure out how to do.
Splitters and tunnels. Okay, so a splitter, let's go back to our thing here.
So let's go to our reader. Okay? So a splitter, what a splitter does, and it's in wiring, you can take a
splitter and it can work either way. Okay? So here's a splitter.
It's an 8-bit splitter. You can see it's a left-handed. The Fan Out is 8.
Input width. So here's the output fan. So this wire here is an 8-bit wire.
Okay? So I can make it, tie it to this. Now every bit here is now one of these bits.
Okay? So bit zero is the rightmost. Let me enable my simulation.
Let's reset it. Okay? So 0 is the rightmost. So when I tie it, you can see the green color changed up here.
It's now 1. Okay? 0, 1, 0, 1. Same with bit 7 is the leftmost.
See on here, 7 is now light green, dark green, light green when it's 1, dark green when it's 0.
Okay? So I can take 8-bit and split it into 8 bits.
Okay, Okay.
Okay, When I enable the simulation here, I can split this into 8 1-bits, so this is 1 8-bit, I can split
it into 8 1-bit elements. Or I can have it work the other direction and taking eight individual bits and put them in and
send them to an 8-bit something. So wires can be however many bits they need to be.
It doesn't matter 1-bit, 8-bit, 4-bit, 3-bit, whatever. And you can use the splitter, okay?
To split them apart or put them together now there is something called a tunnel. Okay, so we're gonna create
a tunnel. Okay, label it DC okay another tunnel
set the other direction we're gonna also label it the
same label DC okay.
Sorry — it says one bit; give it 8 bits.
Hook the other one to this and you notice it works. Okay, so what the tunnel is doing as long as in the same
name it's like there's a wire between them. Okay, so I can use a tunnel anywhere. Okay, so I can use a tunnel anywhere
I can use a我也 Anywhere I need to. Okay, so as long as the names are the same it works the names are different.
It doesn't work, because it doesn't know what to tie together okay, so it's just like I just it is a wireless connection instead
of a wired connection between the two tunnels.
All right, so you can use this to simplify some things I Use them in a couple places just to make it easier to
visualize your circuits. I Don't use it everywhere because.
Those are tunnels and splitters which are also in the lab for you to look at the last one is De Morgan's law.
So De Morgan's law says (A OR B)' equals NOT A AND NOT B So what we want to do is.
See if this works, okay, so How we do that is we build the left side, A OR B, and NOT it. We build
the right side NOT A AND NOT B And compare the two to each other. So if I'm in here, I'm going to build
I'm going to add a new circuit to my project. I don't know what it asks you to call it, but I'm
gonna call it DeMorgan2. Okay, so I have two inputs A and B.
And I have two inputs B and B so it's going to be. This is going to be. Okay, so let me give you
an example it's a.
Now I'm going to enter it here. And I'm going to have a common A and B So I'm going to put this down
here. So I have two inputs. And this is going to be finally What I want to be I'm not going to get to
the rest of this. Okay, so I have a, A or B or gate okay I get output.
Okay, this is one side of the equation oh
and I got A, NOT it sorry not it after I poured it
I need to not it but it NOT gate in this is (A OR B)'.
A OR B okay that's what that output represents the other output is
what I want the other one I want is the output I need is
NOT A and right so what I need to do for this
one I need an AND gate and two things AND gate.
I need NOT A AND NOT B what is
here A, NOT it there's a not
be the same thing for B NOT B.
This output is NOT A AND NOT B all right and so now what I want to do is compare them. All right, so
what I can do is I can use an two-input XOR gate because when XOR gate when they're the same
zero when they're different it's one. Okay, so I can wire these into it and I get
an output.
Here. Okay, so when they're the same zero when they're different when these two results are different it's one so if this ever turns
one then these two circuits are not identical. Okay, so now, the poke tool I run through zero zero
one zero notice the output is always zero, which means this input which is
(A + B)' and this input a not NOT B are always the same — so you get zero, and you would get one if they differed.
Okay, and you can turn that into an LED light so that it lights up when they're different but since they're not different it
never lights up now if we wanted to make them different let me edit these, just to show.
Let's take that NOT gate out now let's run it — notice at 0, 0 they now differ, because the output is one zero one they're different it's one
one zero they're the same so it's zero. Okay, so that shows you how using an XOR to compare two single bits you can
do that to compare them if you want them to be the same it should always be zero under all conditions.
Okay so this is actually the Morgan second law check. Okay, so I have
two circuits driven by the exactly the same two inputs so I only have to cycle these into inputs and I get and I
checked both circuits against each other. All right, so that's De Morgan's second law and you have to do De Morgan's first law so
you have to do De Morgan's second law and you have to do De Morgan's first law all right.
All right, that sets you up. That actually does most of Lab 2 for you need to work through the rest of them
and make sure those circuits get in your file and submit the file for grading.
Okay, so make sure you reach out if you have questions and I should be back next week the jury trial is expected to
end on Wednesday and. And today's Monday, so it's only supposed to be two days.
So hopefully I'll be there. All right, have a great week.